We're at the Masna border crossing,
the crossing point between Lebanon and Syria.
A Babel Doc Pro
There's been non-stop crossfire here for a week.
On one side of the border,
there are people who have been trying to flee the country since the regime change.
They are Shiites,
Alawites and Christians.
They are religious minorities and they are afraid,
convinced that the sunny Islamists,
the new masters of Damascus,
will come after them.
I can speak to terrorists,
but they don't allow us to go inside
Lebanon. If you stay here,
what will happen?
I don't know.
I will pay all my money.
But I don't know what I'm going to do.
Now I am going to Syria to kill me.
On the other side of the border,
there are the people returning to Syria after years of exile.
Like Basma,
who was a refugee in Beirut with her daughter and her granddaughter just a few months old.
She's a businesswoman who runs two dental practices.
I can't believe that after all this time
I can cross this border.
It's my first time in 14 years!
Unlike some people, I've never been back.
I couldn't go back as long as
Bashar al-Assad was there.
As of December 2024,
6 million Syrians have fled their country since 2011 and the start of the civil war.
Like Basma,
a student in Damascus.
She took part in a demonstration against the dictatorship.
She risked imprisonment for doing so,
so she chose to flee.
For her,
this return is a historic day.
All along the road,
there are remnants of the rout of the regime.
We have suffered so much
and today there is nothing but joy.
I breathe in freedom and there's nothing
more precious on this earth.
It's better than the taste of bread
and better than anything!
We are free.
We are free for the first time.
May God protect us.
O Lord.
Two hours later,
Damascus,
and the first memories come flooding back.
That's the area where I was studying.
I was just starting my studies.
It's right here.
My country, my Syria.
But how dare they take it away from us?
My God.
My God, how dare they deprive us of our own country.
My God. But how is that possible?
Al-hamdu li-l-lah, Al-hamdu li-l-lah.
On this day she finds the capital rejoicing and she's going back to the neighborhood of her childhood where she grew up where
she'll find her younger sister her nieces and her cousin who've planned everything to welcome her a PA system in the street and party music
N 15
N 1
She's able to return home thanks to the arrival in power of fighters from the Islamist group
HTS, Hayat Tahrir al-Chan.
They are led by a young commander,
Abu Mohammed al-Jolani.
He's 42 years old and a former jihadist,
labelled a terrorist by the West.
He now embodies both the fears and the hopes of an entire people.
Syria belongs to us, not to the Assad family.
We have destroyed them.
We've finally destroyed them.
For the past week,
since the 8th of December 2024,
Damascus has been celebrating.
The statues of the Assad's father and son have been knocked down and destroyed.
The debris of 50 years of dictatorship lies on the ground.
We have brought down tyranny.
We have brought down the entire
Syrian intelligence and terror system.
It's the end of Bashar
and his Iranian and Russian allies.
The most powerful in the region have fled,
with President Bashar al-Assad and his family the first to go.
Their residence and the presidential palace,
a hitherto inaccessible fortress,
were abandoned to the Syrian people,
who have taken back control over their destiny.
The palace has been emptied,
every nook and cranny searched,
and one wing ravaged by fire.
Here and throughout the country,
portraits of the dictator and his father are being trampled underfoot or burned.
It all began 12 days prior.
For over a decade,
the power of Damascus has been undermined in the northeast by Kurdish forces and in the west by Islamist factions.
It was in the west,
in the Idlib region,
that the offensive was launched.
It was a lightning strike by Al-Jolani and his men.
On 27th
November 2024,
his jihadist rebel group Hayat Tahrir al-Sham
HTS, formerly a branch of Al-Qaeda,
announced the start of its offensive.
The first objective was to take Aleppo,
the country's second city.
The fighting was fierce.
200 people were killed in 48 hours.
After three days,
the city fell to the rebels.
The jihadis then took the road south,
and the towns began to collapse one by one.
In the name of Allah the merciful, I inform you that our
rother fighters have begun to penetrate the city of Hama
Next stop,
Homs,
160 km from the capital.
On the way,
the Islamist rebels took hundreds of supporters of the Assad dynasty prisoner and forced them to sing for the cameras.
Assad damn your soul!
God, Syria, the free army..
God, Syria, the free army...
Finally, on 8 December 2024,
the HTS rebels converged on Damascus and seized strategic positions.
Bashar al-Assad's regime was officially overthrown.
People's first instinct was to go north of Damascus to Sayed Naya prison,
nicknamed the human slaughterhouse.
Tens of thousands of political prisoners were held,
tortured and killed there.
It's the site of the worst atrocities committed by the Assad's in Syria.
We arrive there 48 hours after the fall of the regime.
STAETAO
MAETAO
Including these Turkish aid workers who have been sent to try and uncover all the secrets.
Hidden jails,
secret cells,
kilometers of underground galleries.
This is where we are.
And I think we need to dig over there.
Yes, look at the map.
Given the number of levels,
the tunnel must go at least 10 metres underground.
Be'azid has been coordinating the search since yesterday,
and like everyone else,
YESEV
he's discovering the immensity of the place.
More than 20,000 inmates were locked up in this prison,
subjected to severe abuses.
Those who first arrived on the scene discovered the command centre of the prison complex.
Look at these poor people still here, locked up.
Nearly 200 surveillance cameras suggest the existence of secret corridors and hidden cells.
But they can't find the way in.
So they are digging,
hoping to find survivors still trapped in underground dungeons.
Let's start over here.
Now we're going to start digging at least a metre deep.
We're hoping to find someone.
It's highly unlikely that we will find survivors.
As you can see, there were 3 floors above us
and 3 floors below.
We still can't get in. Whatever's down there
we haven't been able to see yet.
But, according to the former guards, there's a lot.
In any case, we're continuing to search,
trying to get there as quickly as possible.
In the hours following the arrival of the HTS fighters,
the jails were opened,
thanks to them.
Thousands of prisoners were released,
an unthinkable result for these men,
who had expected to die behind bars.
I'm a war veteran. And now I'm free!
Bashar has fallen!
Said Naya.
It was a name that made a whole country shudder until Sunday the 8th of December 2024.
Today,
hundreds of families around the prison are still looking for missing relatives and have no news of them.
Beasid?
Calm down, calm down.
I'm not a soldier.
I'm just a volunteer who's come from Turkey
with my men especially to help you.
Do you understand?
Just before the liberation,
in the middle of the night the day before,
I was woken up by the noise of refrigerated lorries.
I saw men digging a pit, unloading plastic bags.
The smell was unbearable.
They did this all night,
and then the bulldozers arrived.
They covered everything with soil
and hid the tracks so you couldn't see anything.
I went there before that dirty dog Bashar fell
and I know there are bodies there. You have to go there
I understand, ma'am. But that's not our mission today.
Our priority is to find the survivors.
That's our responsibility.
The dead... may God look after them.
How many Syrians have died in Sayed Naya?
NGOs estimate that at least 30,000 people have been executed since 2011.
There are no official figures.
It's the Assad dynasty's best-kept secret.
The bodies of the last prisoners executed in this prison have been transferred to the Damascus morgue.
Ahmed,
24,
is helping families to identify their missing loved ones.
This young intern has just graduated in medicine.
Tell me, what's the position?
They are bringing us bodies that were piled up
at the prison. They are arriving every day.
Many families have been coming.
But none of the bodies were identified.
And were you able to identify any of the bodies?
- At the moment we still have 12 unidentified bodies.
And there are still families waiting for identification?
Yes, there are people waiting outside.
These men are looking for their loved ones.
They've covered their faces.
What are you waiting for?
I'm looking for my brother.
Have you seen his name?
- I've heard that he might be here.
But did you see his name on the list?
- How can I find out?
If you see his name on the list,
you can go in and identify him.
My brother, he's been missing since 2014.
Have you seen his photo published?
No, I was told two years ago that he had been
arrested in the south of Damascus.
He was taken and thrown into the Saydnaya red zone.
I haven't heard from him since.
Families are still hoping to find loved ones in prison more than ten years ago.
I've been looking for him since Friday.
May God punish these criminals!
May he judge them!
May God never forgive them.
He was arrested in the street on his way to the shops.
He was so young.
Her son was arrested while taking part in demonstrations against the regime in 2013.
He was 17 years old.
Trying to find if he's here right now,
but she cannot even identify the faces.
Faces are so distorted.
Because some of the faces of the ex-prisoners,
they used to be put in an acid,
or sometimes they're,
you know,
being burned.
During all these years of repression and torture,
the Assad clan continued to grow even richer.
In addition to the presidential palace,
Assad and his wife owned a villa in an expensive district in the northwest of the city.
Can we come in here?
- Yes, go ahead.
Like many Syrians,
Ahmad is discovering where the dictator lived.
A modern six-story architect-designed villa with a landscaped garden in a well-guarded street.
This was paid off by the Syrians'
blood.
Wow.
Most of the furniture is gone,
but I think it must have been very beautiful.
The villa is now a place where residents of Damascus come to sightsee.
See?
Seems to be wardrobes,
elevator,
bathroom.
This is a balcony,
just a balcony.
Ahmad is part of the Syrian middle class.
He has never seen such a luxurious interior.
This is from the money of the people.
This is from our tax.
This is a whole building.
This is not an apartment.
On the roof of the president's villa,
Ahmed discovers an installation that leaves him speechless.
Oh,
this seems to be an electricity generator or...
The inhabitants of Damascus were only entitled to two hours of electricity a day.
So having a generator was the height of luxury.
e heard about a tunnel, does that mean anything to you
- Yes, there's a long tunnel...
And do you know where it leads?
- I just know there is one. I don't know where it goes.
Maybe,
I don't know,
something secret.
Ahmad discovers an underground network beneath the villa.
There's a corridor and signs that direct the way in what appears to be an exit tunnel.
There are rumours that Bashar al-Assad may have used this tunnel to escape.
A little way from the residence,
Ahmad discovers some cars,
including this vintage Jaguar.
Perhaps this is for Hafez,
not for Assad himself.
Syrians are discovering the hidden wealth of their former leader.
Palaces,
residences.
And among these riches,
an incredible collection of large cars.
In this garage,
there are around a hundred luxury cars.
Mercedes,
Aston Martin.
Different models of Ferrari and
4x4s that were used to transport regime officials.
The Assad family fortune is estimated to be between 1 and 2 billion dollars.
How did the clan get so rich?
It all began in 1970,
when General Hafez al-Assad,
Bashar's father,
seized power in Syria in a military coup.
He overthrew a fragile democracy that had been established nine years earlier.
My dear compatriots, greetings.
Thank you for listening.
Hafez al-Assad established a hardline dictatorship.
Opponents were arrested,
Islamists targeted,
only one political party was allowed,
and the press was muzzled.
The Ba'ath Party leader held Syrian society in an iron grip.
What characterises this regime is ultra-violence,
permanent terror.
All Syrians speak,
and have always spoken, of fear.
This repression,
particularly of the Muslim Brotherhood,
but also of the left-wing opposition that also existed
in Syria, culminated in 1982 in Hama.
There were aerial bombardments,
massacres, atrocities, disappearances.
God is great.
Many foreign heads of state attended his funeral.
Jacques Chirac was the only Western president.
They came to greet the new Syrian head of state,
Hafez's son,
Bachar al-Assad,
taking the place of his brother,
who had died suddenly in a car accident.
God, Syria and Bashar.
The son, Bashar, who at the time was specialising
in ophthalmology in London, was called home urgently.
So he was someone who, on the face of it, was
not at all prepared to take over from his father.
a priori,
was not at all prepared to take the succession of his father.
His wife had grown up in England. So she helped
to develop an image of Syria as opening up.
Throughout their reign,
Bashar and Asma al-Assad put their private life on show,
presenting themselves as a modern couple.
This new image of Syria won admiration from diplomats everywhere.
From Russia to Iran,
Bashar al-Assad became an important interlocutor.
He was received by every head of state.
SYRIAN ARAB REPUBLIC
I have always been convinced that,
while respecting its traditional alliances,
Syria could make a contribution to peace.
Criminal, we hate you.
Get out, you and your regime!
I'm not in the hospital.
Our souls, our blood for freedom.
My brother, they've killed my brother!
By the end of 2011, 8,000 people had already
disappeared into the regime's jails.
This dual system of intelligence services
and prison system is truly characteristic
of the regime of Bashar al-Assad
and his father and sets the Assad regime apart,
if you like, from other dictatorships in the region.
...the regime of al-Assad compared to other dictatorships in the region.
So there was no order to make any attack.
We don't have any chemical weapons.
We gave up our arsenals few years ago.
Even if we had them,
we wouldn't use them.
And we have never used our chemical arsenal in our history.
In my opinion, what characterises this regime
is the violence, the capture of national wealth,
and the total absence of limits to the use of repression.
Hundreds of thousands have died,
probably 600,000 in the 13 years of war.
Mass murder,
embezzlement,
corruption,
but also drug trafficking.
The family has also turned its country into a drug dealing state.
The state has been criminalised,
under Bashar al-Assad specifically.
We know about the regime's role in drug trafficking,
first when it occupied part of Lebanon,
and now trafficking, captagon and so on.
It is a regime that has made itself criminal.
In this warehouse,
thousands of bags were awaiting shipment.
Inside were pills of Captagon,
a psychostimulant nicknamed the poor man's cocaine.
5KVA
SVC
5 KV/
TARG
5KV/
K TARG
sVc
5KVI
KVA
5 KVA
The Syrian state earned between 7 and 10 billion dollars from this trade.
The trafficking was controlled by Bashar al-Assad's brother,
Maher al-Assad,
shown here in the background.
Abu Muhammad al-Jolani has committed to putting an end to it and to destroying all stocks.
To celebrate Syria's new beginning,
the masters of Damascus have called on all the country's Muslims to unite at the Great Friday Prayer.
On that day,
for the first time,
the Muslims of Damascus have been able to get together.
In 50 years,
they will no longer be celebrating the glory of the Assad's.
I want a flag too!
Give me some money for a flag!
30-year-old Razan wouldn't miss this moment for the world.
She's going with her two sisters to the great mosque of Damascus,
the religious heart of Syria for 14 centuries.
Today is all about joy and freedom.
Today is the day of rebirth, it's a great day,
everyone has come to celebrate.
It's for us Muslims and for all the Syrian people.
Also for all the Sunni Muslims.
For us Muslims, Friday is a day of rest,
a day of celebration. The regime deprived us of that..
Of this very special day.
And now we're rid of him.
Bashar al-Assad was a Muslim president,
he should have respected this day.
But no, he had those who went to the mosque
to pray arrested and taken away.
Just because they were going to pray. 3 quarters
of those who were arrested, it was because of that.
The young woman has seen several of her relatives arrested,
starting with her father.
Her whole family lived in fear of being denounced.
When the uprising started,
we all wanted to speak out.
We were carried away by a feeling of freedom
and we realised just how silenced we had been.
Even at home we were afraid to speak out.
We were always saying that the walls had ears.
It got to the point where we were even
afraid for our children,
because even they could be targeted by the regime.
They had no mercy.
I'd like him to suffer as much as we did.
He deserves to be buried where he tortured his people.
Now a stay-at-home mother,
the beautician wants to believe in better days.
We have hope.
The people who liberated us told us:
"This is your country. We just want to pave the way".
We are at the centre of their concerns,
they are helping us, they are very supportive.
I think they want to raise our standard of living.
The time for prayer is approaching.
The young women return to the area around the mosque.
Many of the people of Damascus have responded to the call of the HTS.
This is more than a simple prayer.
It's a gathering of an entire nation.
The regime's new flags are flying everywhere.
Ask where they got their flags.
Look at the crowds around the mosque,
there's not going to be any more room.
Razan was not expecting such a large crowd.
The new prime minister,
Mohammed al-Bashir,
is due to give a speech during these prayers.
So every Syrian wants to see and hear the man who was appointed by the new government.
How do you feel?
The feeling is indescribable. I'm overcome
with immense joy, we're very happy.
We hope that everything will turn out
the way we want it to.
I'm afraid I'm dreaming, that it's all unreal.
I'm really afraid I'm dreaming.
Bashar al-Assad, the people want you executed!
This is the first time in modern Syrian history that a prime minister has addressed the nation from a mosque.
We have done all this to establish a state of law,
a state of freedom,
justice and dignity for all.
We will protect the rights of all the poor in society.
And we will restore dignity to all who have lost it.
Still relatively unknown to the Syrian people,
this engineer by training is tasked with overseeing the country's political transition until the 1st of March 2025.
Will the promises of freedom be kept?
Especially for religious minorities.
Not far from the main mosque,
in the Christian quarter,
the new government is welcomed with a mixture of joy and anxiety,
as is the case with Tala.
Hi Johnny, how are you?
Can you and Sarah come and pick us up
so we can go shopping?
She is about to go out with her sister Sarah and her friend Koko.
Since the HTS took over the country,
The women in this Christian family have not gone out without a man.
Today it's their friend Johnny who'll be acting as chaperone.
There were two million Christians in Syria before the civil war.
Three-quarters have left the country since 2011.
Honestly in the current situation, it's reassuring
if there's a friend with us
because at the moment,
we don't know what can happen.
Until everyone can live their lives as they used to.
I saw a man dressed in a tunic,
a beard and a hat, like an Afghan.
A very big beard and another with his face covered.
It has to be said that the members of HTS
look a bit scary.
You mean physically?
- Yes, physically.
We're not used to this. We've never seen
anything like it. Neither before nor after the crisis.
They go to the supermarket.
Tala,
her sister Sarah and her friend Koko are stocking up because they're worried about what might happen next.
There are rumours of shortages to come.
Let's see what we need at home.
In this local store run by a Muslim family,
they freely express their fears about the fate that the country's new leaders may have in store for Syrian women.
What worries me is the outbreak of a religious war,
or a civil war.
If he starts giving us instructions like
"women, don't go out, don't work, cover up,
don't go out any more".
we are afraid that there will be
no more individual freedom for women.
That we won't be able to go to university,
that we won't be able to work, nothing at all.
That's what we're afraid of.
The shelves are fully stocked,
but inflation,
already high before the fall of the regime,
is taking its toll.
What's most striking is the absence of labels showing prices.
Prices used to be displayed everywhere.
Creme But now there aren't any.
But now there aren't any.
Prices change every day
depending on the value of the dollar.
We don't even have a government
or a minister to regulate all that.
The prices are determined.
So,
Tala learns the prices at the checkout.
How much is the oil now? 2,000?
For the moment,
the price of oil has not changed.
Nor have the banknotes,
which still bear Bashar al-Assad's image.
After shopping,
the group of friends decide to stop for a bite to eat outside.
Soon,
the tension is palpable.
Two dust-covered cars are parked behind them.
They are armed rebels.
I'm nervous. They're all there.
Shall we go?
The
girls decide to leave.
The reason that these jihadists frighten them is that everyone still remembers the Raqqa caliphate.
It was in the town of Raqqa in the north of Syria that the Islamic State established its capital.
From 2014 to 2017,
ISIS imposed Sharia law at its harshest and committed the most terrible atrocities.
For many Syrians,
while the jihadists may use one hand for social action,
they are also capable of using the other to strike without mercy.
The new strongman of Damascus,
Abu Mohammed al-Julani,
once close to the Islamic State,
distanced himself from it in 2011.
He's a chameleon-like figure.
Who really is Syria's new leader?
Meet journalist Wassim Nasser,
the only expert on jihadism to have met him.
When he was very young, in his early twenties,
Jolani went to Iraq to fight against the American
armed forces as a member of al-Qaeda.
He was sent by the late Baghdadi,
caliph of the Islamic State,
to establish what has become the Nusra Front in Syria.
He is on the list of terrorists wanted by the Americans,
with a 10 million price on his head.
Mohamed Al-Jolani officially severed his ties with the Nusra Front,
an Islamist group affiliated with Al-Qaeda.
On the same day,
he launched his own movement,
Hayat Tahrir Al Sham
We declare the complete cancellation of all operations
under the name of the Nusra Front.
We are building a new group operating
under the name of Hayat Tahrir al-Sham.
We affirm that this new organisation
is not affiliated to any outside entity.
The real clash was going to be with the Islamic State.
There were pitched battles, hundreds of deaths
and that's when Jolani achieved independence.
Jolani has taken on a new image.
He's changed his style of dress and no longer appears in a religious tunic.
He sometimes even wears civilian clothes.
He's mastered the strategy of communicating through style,
often military.
We're talking to anyone capable of bearing arms
or anyone capable of doing their duty as a jihadist.
The time to fight is now.
When I went to see Joulani in Idlib,
in mid-2023,
I met a soldier but I also had the impression
that I was meeting a politician.
In his conservative stronghold of Idlib,
Mohamed Al-Julani has to deal with different groups of fighters.
He now manages a city of 4 million inhabitants.
It's not at all a Taliban-style system.
Women have access to education.
So it's more the traditional Syrian code that applies.
That doesn't make him a democrat or a liberal,
he's still a strict Islamist.
We're prepared to die to keep our people safe.
That's our raison d'être.
He came out of the global jihad and became
a player on the Syrian scene.
He said to me "my objective is to retake Damascus
and topple Bashar al-Assad"
And what he said to me was exactly what he then did.
Our brothers in Homs, get ready,
we're coming to every town.
Damascus, Deraa, Deir- ez-Zor.
We'll take them all, inshallah.
With just 20,000 men,
Mohammed Al-Jolani has succeeded in toppling one of the Middle East's most bloodthirsty dictators.
Will he be able to keep his distance from the supporters of an international jihad?
Because,
to take the country,
the HTS brigades fought with independent jihadists at their side.
Like this Frenchman,
who filmed the stages of the conquest,
Down with al-Assad.
Allahu Akbar!
Today there are still around a hundred French people living in Syria.
Even the Christians are happy.
Allahu Akbar.
It's not easy to know how many of them took part in the offensive led by Jolani.
Entry into the city of Latakia. Welcome from
the civilian population. Allahu Akbar.
One of them has arranged to meet us in Idlib,
a seven-hour drive from the capital.
This is the stronghold of Jolani's HTS,
his movement's laboratory,
which could inspire the management of the new Syria.
Compared with the other towns we passed through,
this one seems better run.
The market stalls are fully stocked and all the shops are open.
The police are controlling the traffic.
Unlike in Damascus,
the women we see here are all veiled.
This is Hicham,
a French jihadist from Nice.
His fighting name is Saifullah,
literally Sword of God.
There's a Kalashnikov slung across his back and magazines strapped to his chest.
Although he knows that he's wanted by the French authorities,
he agrees to testify with his face uncovered.
Don't worry.
Although he supports Jolani's offensive,
he says he does not belong to HTS but is independent.
The independents are called "mostakilin".
That's people who are independent but have
a good relationship with HTS.
With everyone.
Whether it's with civilians, with the free army
or with everyone else.
So the control that there is here in the Idlib region,
Idlib is HTS.
They control the territory.
They have to govern by Sharia law, OK.
By divine law, not democratic law.
So what's going to happen, and what's being said,
are two different things. We don't know.
So Jolani's supporters are far from being completely on board with the official line of Syria's new master.
Hisham says he arrived in Idlib eight years ago via Omar Omzan's network.
This jihadist was one of the main French recruiters.
He's said to have rallied around 50 men,
all from Nice and the Côte d'Azur.
This is a neighbour.
One of our neighbours.
How are you, my friend?
How are you? It's been a while.
I'm fine. I saw you from a distance.
Those are our French friends. What do you think
of foreigners like me who have come here?
Very good. They're our brothers.
We have a very good relationship.
They're real brothers!
Hisham heads towards Idlib city centre,
passing through the outskirts of the city.
That's the Idlib stadium.
I think the World Cup will be here soon.
arsa, Messi or Ronaldo may come here. You never knov
He is married here and started a second family.
And for the Frenchman,
everyday life seems almost normal.
You have a vision of Syria, Hiroshima.
It's true that there's war, but there's life.
People need to live, they need to eat,
they need to work.
Children need to go to sport and school like
everyone else, so there you have it.
For example, my wife is a school teacher.
So I let her work.
But I agree that my wife should go to work.
There's no problem with that.
However,
what he's saying is far from the line taken by Joulani and his lieutenants.
Hisham wants the Syrians to follow the Afghan model.
His ideal is the Taliban.
In Afghanistan, they fought for 42 years,
sacrificing their lives and their time.
They lived in fear, joy and famine.
And they managed to take back
the whole of Afghanistan.
And now they are living at home,
with their own rules. OK?
And what a source of pride.
That's something to be proud of.
The Frenchman may have rebuilt his life in Syria,
but he left behind two children in Nice.
Does he intend to return to France one day?
I don't think so.
First of all, I'm not interested in going back
and secondly, what's waiting for me
won't be a hotel room or a cosy home.
I think it will be prison,
so, to avoid that, I'm going to stay here.
Will these jihadists scatter into thin air
because they have no place in this Syrian movement,
as they themselves are not Syrians?
Will they join the Islamic State cells that still exist,
as we know, in northern Syria and Iraq?
as we know,
in northern Syria and in Iraq?
of the HTS brigades.
We're heading for Aleppo,
the first city conquered by Al-Julani.
It came under rebel control after massive bombardment by the Russian air force.
A jewel of Syrian culture,
this is one of the oldest cities in the world.
A UNESCO World Heritage Site,
it has long been the country's main tourist destination.
In the main square,
life is returning to normal among the street vendors.
3 packs of cakes for 10 euros
Here,
while the symbols of the past have been destroyed,
others have appeared.
Notably the new flag,
flanked by three red stars on a green,
white and black background.
Now the flag of the revolution,
it's been the symbol of the opposition since the civil war in 2011.
On the billboards,
members of HTS are already displaying their victory over this historic city.
Abdelhaï Kadoué is an unmissable figure in Aleppo.
This French-speaking shopkeeper and hotelier can't stop talking about his city.
We're in the Bab Antakya souk.
The entrance to the souks, the western entrance
to the souks of Aleppo.
Aleppo?
He wanders through this souk,
the largest covered market in the world,
a maze of 13 kilometres of alleyways.
This thousand-year-old district is packed with architectural treasures.
This was Aleppo's first mosque, in 1637.
It was built on a triumphal arch from Roman times.
Born near Aleppo 67 years ago,
Abdel Hai...
Like the majority of Syrians we meet,
welcomes the fall of Bashir al-Assad's regime and hopes for lasting peace.
I feel happy. I see that people have gone back
to their shops.
And that life goes on.
Life goes on. Even if there aren't many customers
in the souks, as you can see.
it people have hope, and that's the most important thin
Hope for a better future.
The deeper you go into the souk,
the more you see the scars of the civil war,
all the way to alleyways that have been completely destroyed.
In 2011,
rebels opposed to Bashar al-Assad's regime reportedly dynamited and bombed a large part of this historic site.
The Syrians have a very strong desire
to rebuild the city.
This was the most interesting part of the souk.
It was the spice souk.
All the shops sold perfumes, spices,
saffron and spices in general in this part of the souk.
Insha'allah, you will come back and you will see,
now with this new period
without corruption
and with the help of the United Nations, the people
who adore our culture.
It's going to happen soon.
Abdelhai invites us to his home.
He owns a traditional guest house in the old town of Aleppo.
Decorated with Syrian antiques patiently collected over the years,
it has long been a favourite haunt of tourists from all over the world.
But it's now completely deserted.
Before 2011, the five or six 5-star hotels in Aleppo
had around a thousand rooms
and were always full.
Generally all year round, all year round,
I mean all seasons, summer and winter,
I had 90% occupancy.
That means that 15 rooms were full all year round.
15 rooms were full all year round.
It's tolerant, there's calm.
We haven't seen any trouble.
Will they change? I don't know.
For the moment it's fine.
We need order, little by little.
Because I don't know their members for the
administration. But they've left everyone alone.
They've announced that everyone should go
ack to work. The schools are going to open next week
The banks are already open
and next week they'll open again.
And people's money is guaranteed in the banks.
And that's something that reassures people
and is very important for the future.
There were 200,000 Christians before the start of the Civil War.
Today,
there are just 30,000.
There's no denying it.
Eastern Christians have been targeted by the various Islamist factions that have clashed in the country.
Bishop Jalouf,
ordained as Apostolic Vicar by the Pope,
is one of the Vatican's most eminent representatives in Syria.
He himself was a victim of the jihadist rebels.
There have been murders, repression, threats.
Many Christians have been kidnapped
and had their houses and land seized.
nyself have been kidnapped twice and put in prison onc
I have been the target of an assassination attempt.
For 22 years he was a priest in Idlib,
the stronghold of the HTS.
Last year he asked to meet Syria's new leader.
With Christmas just a few days away,
he's very optimistic about Mohamed Al-Julani,
who he believes will be able to unify the country.
We saw him and presented him
with all our problems,
difficulties and persecutions.
Personally, I'm not afraid of the future. But the people
who have lived through the repression are very afraid.
In recent months, the rebels have reassured us.
They have told us that our situation
is not going to get any worse.
They told us "We have not come to invade you,
but to help you live in dignity, in freedom,
in a new democracy, free and sovereign,
where everyone's rights will be respected".
SYRIA
350 kilometres from Aleppo,
in the capital Damascus,
the curfew was lifted four days ago.
In the main square,
every evening,
Syrians are taking the opportunity to celebrate this new page in their history.
The jihadist rebels who used to inspire fear are now the country's new.
It's a joy shared by all Syrians.
We have got the result we wanted, thank God,
and we're going to move forward.
I haven't been to Damascus for 14 years, 14 years,
because that pig Bashar deprived us of it.
For young women like Razan,
the beautician we met at the mosque,
a united country finally seems possible.
Come back, you children of our land.
This is your country. Come back and build it.
Bring it your strength.
Long live Syria!
the young medical intern,
is also here to share in this historic moment of renewed unity among Syrians.
People are indeed celebrating from their hearts.
You know,
it's not just like before,
just fake smiles,
being pushed and forced to just,
you know,
celebrate.
Now people are being happy.
Syria has entered a new,
very uncertain era.
The country is now hanging onto its destiny by a thread.